welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
okay welcome to the stoa everyone i'm
peter lindberg the steward of the stoa
the stow is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most
at the nice edge of this very moment
and uh when i first created the stoa i
envisioned it to
be a space a digital space for us to
have important and difficult
conversations and i was happy when um
i was talking to the brothers who
co-founded
letter dane and clyde who are here today
um about collaborating with um
between the letter platform the
conversations that happened there
and to have conversations on this
digital campfire
uh such as the stoa and uh we came up
with something called postscript
the idea here is that conversations on
the
letter platform popular conversations uh
continue on
uh after fact uh here uh in person
so having the two interlocutors
expressing themselves
uh in a different medium and seeing how
it goes so that's the idea of
postscript and uh i will introduce
uh the two interlocutors today and then
the format in a moment
but first i'll hand it over to clyde
kind of speak on
letter broadly for for people who uh may
not be familiar with it
you're a mute right now and you just use
you can you can unmute yourself yeah
there you go i'm back um thanks peter
for that intro uh i guess for the people
who are not
familiar with leather it's probably two
ways to describe it one is
kind of the mechanics of how it works
it's a place for
any two people to have an exchange
the conversation by the exchange of
written letters
but really it's a place that's trying to
repair the health of discourse by
bringing people together who disagree
but when they disagree view
each other as collaborators rather than
ideological enemies and i know you're
going to be interviewing buster and bj
and i think they're just such
outstanding examples
of the kinds of individuals that are
helping to create a new type of dialogue
online
um you know letter has hosted hundreds
of conversations now
between people who view the world
through different lenses
and i think in reading those
conversations we're all invited to
take a journey to try and figure out
what's true and
i think that overlaps incredibly well
with what the star
is attempting and it's a it's a real
privilege to be
associated with this community and with
you peter so
i'll let you get into the interview um
but then i'll be observing if you only
questions for us
uh at any point either we'll come back
um or you know i'll be here so
tag me in thank you
very cool very cool and i definitely
recommend everyone to check out the
letter wiki platform and uh
if you're inspired to have a
conversation uh from anything you heard
here uh feel free to go on the platform
and you can continue uh the dialogue
there
so yeah today we have uh bj campbell
and buster benson and they had an
exchange on the letter platform called
guns in america
which was their the runner-up for the
impossible conversations that
competition that letter had recently
which just got announced today
so congratulations on the the runner-up
status guys um
buster benson uh allow them to maybe
introduce themselves if they want to
give
flesh it out more but buster is an
entrepreneur writer he wrote a book
called why we're yelling
and then bj campbell he's also a writer
on a blog called hand waving freak outer
rate
and he writes about guns and and
cultural issues
and so what we're doing today is uh
buster will go first for three to five
minutes
he will say his current position stance
on guns in america and then we'll take
in bj
and then they'll have an open
conversation for about 20 30 minutes
and in the chat if you're inspired uh um
to have any questions just write it down
this will go on youtube so if you want
me to read on your behalf
indicate that in the chat and then uh
after the 30 minute mark of the
conversation
we'll uh take in some questions so that
being said
i will hand it over to buster
all right hey everyone i'm super excited
to
be here um i i'm going to try to
summarize what a 14 000 word letter
exchange between bj and i was like
um in three minutes and then bj can
step in and tell me where i've made
mistakes because a lot of it has
it's probably still in my perspective um
so we were introduced
you know we both belong to a community
on facebook that has
you know some of these conversations but
we were introduced to each other by
mutual
acquaintance to have this conversation
on letter about guns in particular
um and i was like yeah sure i'll do that
because i've
i had tried to host salons on gun
control i live in berkeley california
there's
it's really hard to find um people that
are really
willing to take the opposite position on
guns um and so to find someone like bj
who
had not only you know a strong position
but actually very eloquent
and articulate about this position and a
lot of articles on medium
um and i'm super excited to do this um
it started off with just a question
of you know what i think it's called
sort of a pretty
perfectly stupid question which is um
does every single gun sold in america
create
that add to book about add to violence
in the word in the country or
reduce violence in the country um i
stated that purposefully vague because
you could think of you know some people
think of guns as a defense and some
people think of the guns as a menace
and in both cases they want to that's
the
concept of safety is sort of core to the
whole argument around guns and
it is so simple to reduce it down to
like do they just simply
make the number go up or that number go
down um and bj quickly corrected me
and um sort of teased apart and said
like you know there's the suicide number
there's the homicide number there's
you know the just violence in general um
there's like replacement violence that
would happen with guns
um we tried to basically solve this
question
by in several steps teaching apart
like um you know how many how many
um suicides happen how many um homicides
happen how much of accidental how much
is
uh related to the to the policies out
there my position
is and still remains that we would be
safer with fewer guns
um that's you know a position that
um i still feel strongly about but the
question that's really hard that i
really did shift sort of existentially
on this position is
how do we do that um and i think
one of the things that i really learned
from this conversation was it's
you know many of us come to this
question with like let's get rid of
assault rifles let's stop
you know selling them my gun shows let's
do background checks let's you know do
the waiting period let's do all these
things um
a couple things became clear as you talk
to someone like bj is like
well a lot of states already have this
stuff it doesn't necessarily reduce the
guns
the gun violence in this country in
those states
and the the policies that we're pushing
are oftentimes
it's really a hard stretch to imagine
how they would actually impact
the numbers of homicides and sort of gun
homicides
and so we really try to zero in on what
would be the highest impact policy that
we could both agree on
to do this and after a long period of
back and forth we settled on i think
a position around rather than federal
sort of run
organizations with universal background
checks lean on the existing
nics database which people already do
for background checks
and allow states to basically build a
dmv for guns
which means that at point of you know at
point of purchase you have to show your
state um sort of licensed gun purchasing
license
that has already proven that there's
been some kind of background check for
you
but you haven't you're not a fellow and
you're not you know you're not a
domestic abuser
you haven't been deemed mentally ill by
a judge all these things
and then from then on as long as you
have the license you can buy guns
um and by doing the math and bjo will
have much more
like sort of data on this because i was
really you know surfing on his ability
to like produce all this all these
studies that have been made
um this could be this could result
in a five percent reduction um in
in in homicides across the board
and a larger number of just gone
homicides
and because we know this because certain
states have done this
and certain studies have been done to
show how the delta has been reached
in small pockets of the country and
that was you know we ended up coming
down to a five percent reduction
every single state has to do this so
there are definitely challenges but
um and it's not a huge number but to me
making any progress is is the foot in
the door
to making more progress we'll learn
something by doing this if we can do it
it's local
people can decide to um sort of do this
on a smaller battlefield of their state
um and
we can sort of take the conversation
down from this ideological you know
thing in the sky to something more on
the ground
and that really appealed to me and in
the meantime i'll wrap it up quick
um some concessions i think should be
made one of them being like
you know we should also try to tackle
suicides directly we should try to
tackle domestic abuse
directly and sort of you know tackle
these really acute
um sources of gun violence
um in a way that um handles them as
people and not just through policies
and that could also be unstable and then
also things like the ability to to give
your gun to someone else if you're
suicidal
um it's currently illegal um and i think
that could be illegal and so like we had
a couple concessions that were really
small to me but big to be to get because
they are sort of backwards
um and then a couple vice versa where
things that seemed big to
to to me were easier for bj to
to take on because just moving from
federal to state was pretty easy for me
to say
um and anyway that's the summary i think
we can dive into it it's a giant organic
topic
um but we came out of it i think both
feeling pretty jazzed about
um finding a point of agreement and
we have since gone around and tried to
talk to people
on both sides of the position to see if
whether or not they are
you know friendly to it or you know open
to it and
we've found a lot of open ears i think
so far so that's that's my summary
hopefully that was made sense oh cool
so uh we'll hand over to bj now for his
three to five minutes
i might go over three to five minutes
but i'd ask your
uh ask your permission so um
i'm not a writer i'm an engineer i'm a
hydrologist which is
a very statistics-heavy field and
um my entrance into all this stuff
writing and
all the weird paths that have taken me
here tonight had to do with
really about facebook arguments in 2018.
and i kept having to cross post the same
thing over and over in facebook
arguments and i was like why don't i
just
like clean this up a little bit add some
graph stick it on medium that stuff went
viral
and um and then i ended up writing about
other culture war issues and stuff like
that
and as a result of that i got tied in
with a group called open source defense
which is a culture war free gun
rights statistics oriented
um organization um
i've went to went to shot show in
january with them i've written some
articles with them
some of them are tied actually to the
letter
um exchange i might go into that a
second um
from there i've now gotten several
things published in recoil magazine
i got up my first print article in
recoil this past edition in recoil 50
and yesterday this
long chain of events led me to doing a
an over
hour an hour long
podcast style interview with michael
siegel who is the
gun research guy at boston university
who studies that i was
heavily referencing in my letter thing
with buster
and it was an amazing experience
and through all of this what i've found
is that if you have
open dialogue that is looking at
statistics
and you're willing to set ideology at
the door
you come to um some resounding
conclusions about what we can do and
what we can't do
and what kinds of things we can give
back to gun owners to convince them that
um that
the gun control people are coming into
the are argument with good faith
and this is something that michael
stressed heavily in the um
in the interview i did with him
yesterday which i believe will be live
on recoil tv
next week sometime and
his position as someone who is deeper in
the numbers than
me or buster was that
generally there are some laws that have
been shown to work
most laws have been shown explicitly not
to work
and that we can probably get the laws
that do work
past if we give the candy back that
they stole and that part of that
is but the most important thing to get
to that point is that
um is earning the respect
and faith from gun owners so that they
can get behind board because they feel
like they've been burned
i bet they've been burned a lot and when
the an ordinary gun opera opens up some
immediate piece that says something
about a gun policy researcher they're
just like yeah fuck it and they throw it
away
right and further i mean
michael was very critical of um some of
the things that people are that
politicians in the media have been
saying like be you know beeto
and his you know yes we are coming to
take your guns it's like well this isn't
helping
and there won't you know so when you the
reason it isn't helping is obviously get
into the numbers because the stuff
they're talking about taking isn't
responsible for any of the deaths
right you know i think you know uh
rifles are responsible for like one
percent of gun deaths in the country so
the whole argument about rifles it's
basically a red herring it has to do
with what's scary and it has to do with
playing to
people's fears to try and get votes or
to try and get clicks
right you know and one of the problems
that the gun
discussion has now is that
um it has pivoted into this
instead of it being about um
trying to save lives it's about trying
to attack cultures
and michael became very aware of this
recently through this
most recent study that he did this thing
ah there it is um he this is uh this is
available now and it's it's free it's
from the american journal of
preventative medicine and it was a poll
that he
did uh with some research to be a
follow-up poll next year to check on it
um and it's called the meaning of guns
to gun owners in the united states the
2019 national
lawful use of guns survey so this is
part of what his group at boston
university has done and his group
of all the researchers that are doing
this stuff they're approaching it from
the least ideological and the most
mathematical position
and i really appreciate all the work
that they've done
even more than a lot of the other ones
that i've read if you're gonna go and do
your own homework
f dig up michael siegel see what
whatever he's written and whatever his
group has written that he has his name
on it it's gonna be good stuff
um and the conclusion generally like
part of this is about us our position um
in in the whole deal is is kind of this
the mathematics is this
um gun policy that addresses the
features of guns
doesn't matter doesn't work um if
somebody's going to murder somebody else
they're going to murder
them with whatever kind of gun they have
whether it has a pistol grip on the
front or not
whether it's an assault rifle or a
pistol most of the school shootings that
we've had could have been
just as easily done with the glock nine
millimeter that's on the side of
every police officer as with a
scary-looking rifle
these kinds of things right um the stuff
that
does work is the stuff that addresses
who gets the gun so um
universal background checks for instance
are something that are shown to work
and the reason why is because you know
about ninety percent of guns that are
sold they have a background check anyway
you have to get a next check when you go
to the store to buy a gun
the other remaining 10 percenter
peer-to-peer gun sales from one gun
owner to another gun owner
and those don't have a background check
i couldn't get a background check if i
wanted i wanted to sell a gun to a
friend i don't have the ability to
background check him
and when most universal background check
laws are proposed
they are proposed with this writer
attached that says and also we're going
to have a national firearms registry
and that's the thing that causes all the
gun owners to freak out and
one of the things that siegel did in
this in this study is that he
looked at the opinions of gun owners
about different kinds of gun laws
and it was the support for universal
background check was very high
but he also disaggregated that and said
the per the support for a national gun
registry is very low
so if those things can be pulled apart
by the policy makers they might be able
to get one through without having to tag
the other one on it's kind of like a
trojan horse thing that they keep doing
and they don't under
i think that maybe either they don't
understand it or they're trying to sneak
it in one of the two i wouldn't
know to to speak to them about it um and
then the other thing it
that is i think an important piece of
the puzzle is that
since we know all those other laws don't
work if you package that up
i mean you know if you're talking about
compromised positions
give all that other stuff back you know
let the people in california have their
ar-15s with their drum magazines because
those laws against those
literally don't work because nobody uses
those in crime anyway you can't knock a
liquor store over with a big
unwieldy gun you have to have something
to hide in your pants right you know
so the um so there's a lot of stuff that
can be given back
while you ask for the things that are
worth it another thing that
always pops in in sigel's research is um
there's not a lot of states that have
done this but there's a few that have
um they will add people who have violent
misdemeanors
to the next check so if you've got a
you know a misdemeanor battery on your
record you know maybe you don't need to
buy a gun right
and most gun owners are cool with that
like yeah okay keep the gun out of that
guy's hand i don't want him at the
shooting range with me right so
there's things that can be done but the
things that can be done have to focus on
the kinds of people who end up with guns
and not on what the shape of the gun is
that you're allowed to buy
right and that's the um and so you can
give
all this stuff back while asking for
this other stuff it's the kind of
position that you would be able to go
forward
and the thing that um that siegel beat
on the most
was that in order for the gun owning
public to get behind this
the gun-owning public has to have trust
that the
uh gun policy research are entering into
their research in good faith and some of
them
don't appear to be doing that by my read
of some of the studies michael is
because of his like you know he was a
tobacco researcher for many years
and his approach to tobacco research was
not to
demonize tobacco users it was to enter
into it as if we're trying to reduce the
number of
dead tobacco dead smokers right
you know that's one of the reasons for
instance off on the side he's very pro
vaping and um gets frustrated when
the cdc comes in as an with an
anti-vaping stance because
of the same kind of thing right you know
instead of it being against
gun culture have it be pro
safety and the um the other thing that i
think is important to mention with me
and buster's dialogue
and is that you know homicides are only
a third of the problem
one-third two-thirds are suicides
two-thirds of gun deaths in the country
are people
intentionally killing themselves with
their own guns it doesn't matter what
kind of gun you have to do that a one
bullet gun will do that for you
it ain't like you're gonna miss and
while three uh men outnumber women
three three to one in suicides they
outnumber women
seven to one in gun suicides and female
suicides
aren't uh correlated at all with gun
ownership rates but male
male suicides are so there's something
unique about the male mind
and what leads them to suicide it's
probably hastier and
you know when you make a hasty decision
with a gun you don't have time to undo
the decision
right and the gun
gun culture is slowly becoming aware of
this but it's the one of the most
important things to reducing overall gun
deaths in the country is for gun culture
itself to understand the suicide problem
and you know if you could you know you
could reduce
gun suicides by twenty thirty percent
you can save more people than are
uh you could save two or three times the
number of people number of overall
deaths as they're in domestic homicide
in the whole country
on a yearly basis um and the most
important thing about that is making
sure that
uh that is stigmatized
yeah let's let's let's get to exchange
um is there anything else before safe
europeans okay
that's fine that's the suicide thing is
the biggest thing that we need to do
we need to focus on so so now there's
going to be a 20 minute portion between
buster and bj i'll head over to buster
and then i'll jump in
and then we'll go for some q a
yeah i mean that's so interesting i mean
that's so
um i can't wait to hear what your
conversation was with him um
i i think that
the the thing that seems so like obvious
to
coming out of the conversation that
wasn't obvious
it just seems too small to really have a
big impact is
that why don't why don't we self-reflect
on our policies
actually try to disentangle just the the
position
of every single policy must be pushed
because we just
have to get momentum in that direction
and it will create a snowball
because that's not how it works what we
have to do is really be smart about the
policies we have to roll back for the
ones that
have been proven not to work um the ones
that are the sticking points that people
still feel resentful for because they're
bad policies
that you know punish people for the
wrong reasons
um and just because we they can't relate
to them
and that's such a it seems small but i
think it's the the key here right to get
people
to actually um
trust that there is some kind of not
only one-way push from both sides it's a
two-way
it's a two-way give-and-take um and
i don't know how that happens with
large groups it can happen with
one-on-one conversations and i think
that's why
we got there but when even in a
one-on-one conversation where i'm trying
to represent my demographic and my sort
of
like my position group um i
you do revert back to that like i'm just
gonna push for everything
um and try to whack you as much as i can
on your weak points
um but it's just so unhealthy it's so
unproductive
and we don't
make any progress in the conversation
that way so
um two people that are trying to have
these kind of conversations i think
you know one of the things that has uh
has worked for us
in this conversation and in other words
is just to right up front
try to listen to the criticisms that
seem obviously
accurate and unimportant right because
those are oftentimes things like
um that you know that's we think so
little of them because they're not
important to us but it's really
important to somebody else
um and if we can give those back that's
the first sort of
sort of a gift into the conversation to
the dialogue that then creates the good
will because you have to generate this
good will
somehow and this is one way to do it
other than like establishing a really
long relationship with that other person
and trusting them as a human
your gifts are one way to it's like why
we do this in diplomacy why we do it in
other
sort of traditions um and
you know i think in fact in our
conversation bj was the first one to
make concessions to me which
you know it was and it was shocking how
effective it was for like like just sort
of softening
my tone a little bit because he was
talking about things that were
a little bit over my head in terms of
policies and and organizations and data
and then in a follow-up letter he said
like oh actually i i double checked that
thing i said two letters ago
um and that was wrong um i forget
exactly what it was um about but i think
it was about the uk
um sort of violence rates um in the
beginning and
where they weren't actually measuring
apples and apples and i
didn't dig deep enough to actually
confirm that but he volunteered that as
this information right up front and that
was
so eye opening for me i think it really
opened the conversation up because
when you can volunteer to like expose
your own mistakes
um suddenly you realize you're on the
same side
and that's that's a position where these
conversations can happen
so most of the shifts i made i think
sort of like policy wise were things
that i don't even care that much about
um and and i don't like i i ca and we
both care about the same thing which is
reducing
you know death and violence and homicide
um
so those are that was just a really
standout thing for me um
and i feel lucky to have like been in
conversation with bj because i've had
you know in my background i did a bunch
of salons in my house
and tried to do them online around gun
control
and it's so hard to even get people into
the same room because
everyone thinks it's a trap everyone
thinks that like oh you're
you're gonna you know pretend to be
friendly
and you're gonna bring all these people
in that you disagree with and then
you're gonna attack them
um and that's just a sign of like how
much bad will
is fostering in this like we're not only
um
strong and sort of entrenched in our
positions but we have given up on even
talking to the people because we think
they're
going to come in and um not even talk to
us as humans
so that's that's one thing that sort of
at the meta level like
it it was really nice to to find bj
and find other people on letter that
have this ability to
sort of be in disagreement
and also admit mistakes admit sort of
the weak points and invite people to
come in and
tweak them and try to figure out what's
going on there so michael was worried
about that with the recoil interview
yesterday he
you know the first thing he asked me was
like art you know is rico gonna
chop this up and edit it he was worried
that it would be an
hour discussion and then they would cut
five minutes out that was the most
uh uh undermining or whatever take stuff
out of context or whatnot because that's
what media does nowadays that's like
they give you an hour and and they and
they do whatever
um that's why podcasts are so great yes
yeah absolutely absolutely and i've
i've got i you know might be putting my
foot in them out there i really hope
that recoil doesn't do that with what
i'm going to give them because i'm about
to pass them an hour and 20 minutes but
every they've been very positive very
open about it and
um and so i think that they're um i
think they're
i doubt that they'll do anything like
that but you know i think that they're
probably
possibly unique in the in the gun media
space that
it being a a you know an outlet that
wouldn't do that
right um because that's how the wars are
fought
the wars are fought by taking people out
of context and sticking them in media
and then trolling and then
splashing that into an echo chamber and
trying to get the echo chamber to share
it around
right this is the thing that that kind
of pivoted me away from writing about
guns and into writing about media
criticism and culture war stuff my
personal blog because i started to see
what
once i got five or six articles into the
into writing and stuff and i started to
see which ones got traffic and which one
didn't
the stuff that got the traffic was the
culture war stuff was anything that's
useful in a cultural argument the arms
dealing
in the culture war is what makes you
money in
our modern media landscape because um
that's what people share in facebook
and so that connection
is tremendously unhealthy and it's not
just in the gun space it's in
all of the spaces it's everywhere it's
about everything whether you keep a
school
open or closed for covet or whether you
um you know or
any of it all of it it's always that
it's like what how can i turn this into
a culture war weapon to get clicks out
of it is the first thing that
you know journalists nowaday does
and um that's horribly interesting
it's horrible interesting to see how
even like the pandemic like at the
beginning we were all thinking that like
this we all have this in common we don't
want to get sick and die
we want each other to get to kundai and
then it collapsed into these polarized
sort of political positions around masks
and about
you know sort of you know your personal
freedoms and and i was i was surprised
i was at first i was surprised that that
didn't happen immediately because i was
just
well i think it happened when people
started talking about coming off the
lockdown i think that was from the first
thing
everybody bought into the flattening the
curve and then once the curve was flat
and
icus weren't overloaded then suddenly
that
that was right when it got polarized was
it's like okay now it's time to get on
with business
and then people are like no we have to
extinguish the disease
and there are people like it's not
extinguishable in that way and then at
that point everything
everything got turned into a first stem
thing and and then it helped
the experts like just uh turned out to
be
highly competent and then ultimately
wrong around masks um
that was not just against well not just
the masks but the imperial college
projections on where things are going to
go turned out to be wrong
you know there was a lot of because you
know i mean you're kind of rolling dice
with this thing anyway nobody really
knows anything about it
you can't predict something you've never
seen before right and so
yeah that was and i don't want to turn
this whole thing in a covid you know we
should still talk about guns instead of
covet but
um that was just one example of the that
happens on every space and it has been
happening for a very long time
and um it's it in my mind it all goes
back to that
when i talked to michael yesterday he
was
i asked him this specifically i'm like
do you think
that you can get that you know you can
use this research that you've done
because his conclusion was basically
that you know
uh gun policy reacher search need to do
better about reaching out to gun people
and understanding gun stuff and and
yielding the fact that it's okay to buy
a gun and then let's talk about what we
can do instead of what we can't
because you can't reduce the you can't
reduce number guns the united states
it's just
it's not feasible um you could you know
there's some argument that if you get
we're able to get the united states down
to the boundary area where like
england is that you might create enough
scarcity to where
criminals could buy guns find a gun but
we've got so many guns here right now
you could
magically evaporate half the guns in the
country and a criminal could still find
five if they needed them we've got so
many that that's just
not an attainable goal and and that
would be true whether i was pro-gun or
anti-gun
you know you got a lot of guns around
here and yeah
so um but what he was saying was that
um policy researchers need to be you
know
he thinks he thought the policy reachers
could be more honest could be more open
could enter into things with a little
bit more faith and could try and prove
to the gun people that there is good
faith there
and i was like do you think that would
extend to the politicians he says yeah i
think so
and i just i didn't want to disagree
with him in the interview
um but i disagree with him i don't think
it
that jump is is i don't think that he
can
that it can make that jump and the
reason why i don't think it can make
that jump is because of the
the media engine and the politics engine
the feedback on each other
if they don't if you find it some if you
find a conclusion they'd want to hear
on either side then they're not going to
listen that's i mean i find that helpful
i mean i think
the reason i'm so interested in
productive disagreement as a skill that
you
develop and you practice is because it
has to be bottoms up it has to be
something that you practice individually
and as soon as you know we sort of amass
enough people that can that have the
skill then the politicians have to get
in line because they're there to
represent the people
um would we only project our worst sort
of um
sort of cynical you know nightmarish
hellscape you know
world onto our politicians and ask them
to be our you know our
our generals then that's what to become
um and somehow we have to work with
ourselves and figure out like how do we
create more productive conversations in
the streets in our rooms in our
you know you know in our families and
our friend groups um in our online
interactions
do you think that's possible on a large
scale yeah i think i mean
it's one of my like most hopeful
probably beliefs i mean be optimistic
but
i think i've seen it happen to
individuals and
you know the fact that this exists at
the store exists and like medical
mediation
all the stuff that's coming to you know
i i know you still think it's like a
tiny little bubble
in a gigantic grass sea but the fact
that that bubble wasn't there two years
ago
and now it is um i think is is hopeful
because
these things do have to first appear as
a bubble and then they
can become you know a bigger thing but
yeah maybe
i mean my my perception of you know the
stoa and of
you know productive disagreements and
letter to wiki you know that kind of
thing is i feel like
i feel like there's this giant war
that's happening in a big battlefield
and then when people get injured enough
from the battlefield they wander off
into the woods and then they meet each
other and they sit down and they talk
about why they're roaring and they think
it was kind of stupid and they figured
they'd rather talk it out instead of
participating the war
but i don't think there's very many
people out back here in the woods with
us
and i wouldn't i wouldn't call us the
wounded and i think
there is still hope and optimism that
you wouldn't have if you were just
dying in a ditch in the woods right like
i think these i think some of the people
in doing this kind of thing are some of
the
most you know the kindest strongest like
honest most authentic people in the
public
um sphere right now but oh i agree with
that
i agree with that but you know the fact
is i mean i don't know what might i want
to say the fact that that's that's
inferring in fact that
maybe it's not true i don't know but my
perception is that
the fact that what we have here let's
say for instance that we're
the you know the kind of most thoughtful
most so in such people and we're off
here into what's talking
you know are you sure you can get all
those people in
in the field over here i don't think you
can i'm
i'm i am pessimistic that you can get
that many of them off the battlefield
and i'm curious what strategy you'd like
to do to get people off that battlefield
i think letter.wiki is an interesting
approach and i think that what they
nailed
first off was that a lot of the reasons
why people are warring is because the
user interface
right it's ui based like when you get
into a letter to wakey conversation
you're kind of
forced to be explanatory and forced to
be kind
and you're funneled into a better
version of speaking than
on twitter where everything is just
about who can farm the most clicks from
hot takes
but but uh you know even even that aside
you know how many how many people in the
public discourse right now could even
you know
uh even have the skills to step up and
engage in a letter
the wiki exchange i don't know that
there's that many people that do anymore
i'm worried about that
well that's what's at skill we have to
develop i think that even more important
than the ui
is the design the incentive structures
of the platforms themselves
and you know just hearing clyde ending
talk about how
they want to build how they sort of
create the incentives for themselves to
most likely encourage them to build a
platform that most of the most likely
develop these skills and people
i think that's you know where you know
you know i was at twitter for five years
and i i saw how like when the incentives
are to
um get people to click on ads um
it just informs every single one of your
decisions and it puts the power into the
wrong place
um the fact that they're trying to now
think about a you know pro
account kind of thing um and are
you know you know they i think they
admit that
facebook and twitter and youtube have
have
severely damaged our culture um in many
ways
that you know maybe they didn't intend
to but they did and it's time
i think they are starting to commit
themselves to to changing the incentives
for themselves and their their companies
are going to move fast if they want to
um i don't know if they want to but they
could if they
that was had reached that point um in
their
their shift this might be a good point
to
pivot to some questions in the chat box
um let's go oh
oh man okay megan had a good question
yeah yeah megan had a really good
question let's go with megan first
um thanks both um to me there's a sticky
point
in the in the background check idea
which is about
um about mental illness um on the one
hand obviously that really does need to
be part of a background check but um on
the other hand
i think that it has huge potential for
weaponization um the definition of it is
really subjective
um there's some shady stuff going on
with pharmaceuticals that's affecting
the definition of what's a mental
illness
um and then there's you know the
opinions of you know our neighbors
as someone else pointed out you know
what your neighbor can report you um and
it becomes
extremely subjective and uh potentially
weaponizable
um i i can't really see a solution to
that to that problem there is that
something that either of you have some
thoughts you could share with us
hi good morning i'll they're going to be
quick but i think you know more about
this than i do but
i think that's why we put that aside
to a large extent like you know all the
studies that have been made are about
existing structures that exist like so
the next database does have a mental
illness
i think it's just like if you're in if
you're judged mentally unfit in a court
of
law or by judge which is a lot further
you know away than um you know you're
you're on you know prozac or something
um so
by just saying that like the data we we
found showed that
even at that like really extreme level
um
that there that it could still impact
the the homicide rate the violence rate
once we have more nuance and i think
that's
a follow-up question like if this works
to reduce finance
and we can continue to start to
collaborate with each other on policy
then addressing mental illness like much
bigger problem
i think than even guns
me and michael talked about red flag
laws in the thing yesterday
and um red flag laws were surprisingly
popular in his poll which i thought was
i was very surprising because all the
gun owners i know freaked out about red
flag laws
and uh the
the devil with those things is in the
details right
so if um what michael was advocating in
the discussion was
you know it's like okay if you decide
because red flag laws are mostly meant
to protect
suicidal people and
if you're a family member you discover
that you know your
dad or something like that is having
suicidal thoughts or tendencies or
something like that you might want to
you know get your family member red flag
get the guns out of the house or
something like that
and michael's approach was that his his
understanding of those things was that
it was voluntary that they would come
and say
would you like us to hold on to your
guns for you voluntarily and then they
say yes
so that might not be so bad right um if
you
if it gets up to the point where your
neighbor can call you can you know red
flag you because they know you have guns
and they're pissed off that you didn't
mow your lawn for two weeks
that can be a very different thing and
so the devil in the
in in the details of that is is really
extreme
the other problem with just talking
about um
uh you know in the united states it
would be untenable to
flag somebody for a next check for being
on a
psychoactive drug because a
huge number of people in the united
states are on this damn drugs
it's like 20 or 30 percent or something
like that it's out right now
don't quote me on that look it up and
whatever number you look up is going to
be you're going to be like
you're kidding me it's outrageous how
many of how many people are on a routine
uh pharmaceutical and that has
psychotropic
effects you know and you'll often see oh
well you know the mass shooter he had
that he was taking this drug or that
drug or whatnot and it's almost like
well gracious so is everybody else and
so and then you know the other thing
that goes that ties in with that too
is that if you were to come up with a
law that said that anybody had suicidal
tendencies got their guns taken away
unilaterally by the government
then less people who are gun owners
who were having a rough patch would seek
treatment
and you've created a disincentive for
them to seek treatment in the first
place which makes things worse instead
of better and that's got to get taken
into the discussion too
so it's very yeah it is as sticky as it
gets
you're absolutely correct it is so
sticky and but all those things have to
be factored in
and in some cases state laws like you
know buster mentioned um
you know uh you know you're not allowed
to exchange guns it's
um i can hand my guns to a friend to for
safekeeping in georgia
today no problem if i were living in
california i would have to
take them to a gun store i'd have to
take my friend to a gun store
they would have to run the background
check on the friend they'd have to hold
the guns there for the
whatever the waiting period is before
they can give them to the friend
and then if i ended up committed for
some reason between now and the time
when i wanted my guns back i might be
prohibited from getting the back
and so all of those things would tend to
make it so that i as a california gun
owner would just not do any of that
right um so they they act take
that problem and they make it worse now
does that worstness show up in the
statistics
i can't say yes i don't know for sure
i don't know anybody studied that deeply
i tried to look at it a little bit and i
didn't see
much difference so i don't know the
answer to that like i'm going to put
that out
um but intuitively it would seem to me
that some of these things were
supposedly passed for people safety
you're making them more
unsafe because they weren't totally
thought out about the um the unintended
consequences of them
so that's it it's a very complicated
thing that needs to be teased out and
and people we need to be honest about it
you know yeah whenever i have this
conversation i think
the i always nine out of 10 times i come
away thinking that i know
a lot less about anything than i do more
like we have we tend to
in our own you know time come up with
pretty simple
cl you know and confident positions
about things and then
if you actually look at how hard it is i
think it's okay to feel this feeling of
like
oh man there's there isn't an easy
solution here let's not even try to
solve that one yet let's try to
you know let's work on the easier ones
and that's okay i think because
you know we're not gonna this problem's
not gonna go away um and if we tackle
the hardest one first and we get it
wrong because we're not good at this yet
then that's gonna disincentivize us from
continuing we're
like oh that we tried that you came up
with something stupid that didn't work
we're not going to try that again so i
really like trying to focus on the
the lower hanging fruit as we develop
the skill
before we go to another question i think
there's something else to insert here
and that is that
not everything requires a government fix
some things can be fixed culturally
and that particularly with the suicide
thing that's something that can
you we can make a lot of progress inside
the gun community
just culturally with awareness and
things like that
um and uh and i've i mean i know if i'm
working with one group that's working on
that um i might end up re
interviewing them for recoil um and
there's at least one other group
um uh i think his name is dan voss and
and voss and pinker got together this is
the
former head of the brady campaign
abandoned the brady campaign because he
was so sick of the people at the brady
campaign attacking gun culture instead
of trying to save gun owners lives
and joined up with a prior gun rights
advocate
who is kind of a lightning rod himself
to come up with you know cultural
solutions to the suicide problem
and uh so that's but but that's
relatively new
and so the some of the in cultural like
enculturation effects of trying to fix
that problem
just among us on our end are in the
early stages and might
bear fruit sometime soon we'll see
cool nathan you had a question on the
black market
nathan pierce
if you're going to mute yourself
nope he says it doesn't work his work
okay um
well i find his question dane um
you have some interesting questions for
both bj and buster could you and meet
yourself and ask them
yeah can you guys hear me yep
um well i had a question for buster
first i was wondering whether you
own a gun personally and um and if not
uh does the clinical turmoil
and all the riots and uncertainty in the
united states
make you more inclined to want that sort
of self-protection
yeah i don't own a gun um my grandfather
owns a bunch of guns
a couple of my aunts and uncles do i've
fired guns i've gone to shooting ranges
i've shot you know
cans in the hills and you know i had a
bb gun when i was a kid
but i don't have one i don't plan to get
one i think you could probably say that
you know one of the things that really
changed my position on this actually
early on was to say like well what if
what can i do to make you know guns
um less uh less proliferating everywhere
um i was like what if i what if there
was a contract that i could sign
to like wave my right to guns
permanently
um and would i do that and the answer
was no and it made me think like okay
well
i want the right to have a gun i just
don't want to have a gun
and then it sort of fit into this other
many other sort of positions i have
like yeah i don't want to do that but i
don't want to remove the right to have
it
and especially when i start thinking
about domestic violence and women
in you know abusive relationships like i
think that's one of the only
demographics of people that if they do
have a gun
they're less likely to die and
like so i would never want to unevenly
roll this out and say like you know you
know women can't have guns that would be
terrible like
you know you know minorities and sort of
disenfranchised people can't have guns
like that
that would be terrible you really have
to start with the people that have the
most power
and work your way down um which means
that
you know but that said like i don't have
one i don't plan to have one i probably
became a little bit more likely to get
one
um when you know as like these federal
agents are coming to oakland or you know
portland
like but i'm i'm still thinking i'd be
more likely to kill myself or my family
than anyone else
or by having one
and then the question i had for both of
you was um
you know because i read the conversation
again recently for the competition
and it was so awesome and i felt like
real progress was made
but it's not clear to me how that
translates into
you know the real world you know um and
i wondered what
your take is uh both of you on what the
future of gun law actually looks like
in the united states if you were to kind
of put on your
uh predictor app
do i give a try um
you know gracious uh well okay so first
off
i can probably take a couple of
sprinkles from buster's last question
and and put it in and talk about
gun ownership changes in the past six
months due to uncertainties
um we had a huge gun buying spike in
april
we had another one in may another one in
jean
and um and
the the spikes were not we've had gun
buying spikes before in the united
states and it's usually something like
oh my god hillary's about to win i have
to buy a rifle that she's going to ban
right you know that's usually the form
that they take
and these are familiar to gun store
owners
and what was really curious about the
covid gun buying spike
was and i'm talking about it was insane
their
you know gun stores were just cleaned
out you had little old ladies buying 357
magnums because there's only thing left
they were just like sell me any gun you
have
right that's what happened united states
in the in their rush decoded once
everybody started getting freaked out
you know it was and and the gun store
owners were talking about their you know
these are the toilet paper buyers they
have to protect their toilet paper
right it's all connected
and um the the curious thing about this
was that
these are almost overwhelmingly new gun
owners
and if you look at the number of guns
that have been sold and this new gun
owner trend has
has carried because you had you had the
the russia back coveted then you had the
rush about the
you know uh the the protests then you've
got once the riots started turned
violent then you had another spike
and um and it's not just you know it's
not it's not just conservatives a lot of
liberals are buying them too
um i've had personally i've had several
friends i have one friend who's a
hippie lives in a mountaintop and you
know asheville north carolina guy's been
to a hundred dead shows call me on the
phone
ask me what kind of gun to buy okay um
if you look at the overall numbers and
you follow nssf
estimates of how many are new um
if you were to take a random sample of
20 gun owners in the united states one
out of 20
bought their gun this year
what you see in policy
is that generally places with a higher
gun ownership rate
have less gun laws and
and sometimes you'll see uh studies
research studies they're like look
there's less gun
deaths in states that have you know
higher gun loss but that's probably just
related to the fact there's fewer gun
owners
so there's less people with access to a
gun or whatever and
their reason and and it's it's a reverse
thing it's the people the
states with more gun owners are more
inclined to vote against
gun laws right so the fact that the
number of gun owners is growing and it's
going to be a tremendous spike
the likes of which we have never seen
probably in at least the last 50 or 60
years on a differential basis
this year is going to impa impact how
many gun laws get passed
and um so there's that um the next thing
is that you know where where gun
laws go nationally it's going to depend
who wins all right and we don't know
who's going to win
um the biden has adopted
a general gun control position that is
very similar to what the
uh um
the state legislature in virginia
adopted and a lot of those guys won
and they're so virginia's generally a
red state flipped below this past time
around back during the midterms
uh democratic governor and uh now they
have a democratic majority in their
state legislature
but that democratic majority lives
almost entirely outside of washington dc
and in the richmond suburbs and around
norfolk the whole rest of the state
geographically is
red okay but there's enough population
in those centers where they control it
they walked in and they dropped an
entire uh
the their first you know legislation
period they dropped a stack of
gun laws that were this thick they're
going to pass these 10 different gun
laws right
and you know they they ran on it that's
when they got elected
and what happened there was that
every county outside of those counties
that had those
democrat things they all declared
themselves sanctuary counties they said
we're not
we're not going to enforce these laws if
he passed them it was a huge
deal and there was a lot of friction
about it this whole thing was going
around in january
and right before they started voting on
them there was a big protest in richmond
where over 30 000 i think the official
number was 24 but i've talked to some
people who are down there and they said
over 30 000 people marching peacefully
with
open carrying air 15 rifles walking up
and down the street right
and nobody got shot they cleaned up
after themselves they left they didn't
break anything but
um you know and then when all the the
counties went sanctuary
you know a lot of the legislatures the
legislators they passed some other laws
but they didn't pass that assault
weapons ban because they were they were
scared to they were like it's not gonna
work how are we gonna enforce it
you know the number of people who showed
up at that rally
was on the order of five times the total
i think it was five i have to go back
and look the total amount of
active duty national guard in virginia
so how they're going to enforce that
stuff they can't right so
if biden gets elected interest to push
that stuff
then you're going to see some flavor of
that happen at the national scale
um if trump wins then
um it's like well so first off before
trump
before the election it's likely that
trump's going to rattle off a bunch of
executive orders that clean up some gun
laws and stuff like that that they're
buying votes from gun owners um
afterwards i don't think he's gonna do
anything else than what's already done
and i also don't think by my read on the
current supreme court
i don't think that they're gonna grant
uh uh
any of the the major gun cases that are
brought up
for the supreme court um i don't think
they're going to
rule them even though technically
there's kind of a republican majority if
you want to call them that on the
current supreme court
because i don't think they necessarily
have the
votes to try and push any major second
amendment stuff so i think if trump wins
we're going to be about the state we are
now
um and i think if biden wins we're going
to see some kind of national replay of
what happened in virginia and
that's my read on it i don't know
whether it's true or not but you asked
me to speculate so there it is
cool so we're approaching the hour
so we're going to end shortly do you
guys have any closing thoughts before i
close out today's session
i really like the questions in here that
we didn't get to as well so i
i'm bummed to get those but uh i'm
always open to a conversation on a
letter
if you anyone talks about anyone wants
to talk about it um about this stuff
and uh yeah it's just i see this as like
one doorway into a complex problem which
is
what i always just think of as just the
the inability to have conversations with
people
because if we can't talk to people that
we disagree with
everything is going to break all the
conversations are going to fall over
um guns is a hard one but so it's
immigration so is you know
every every other you know education and
health
health care and all these things have
the same exact problem and
if we expect the politicians to solve it
for us we're going to be waiting a long
time we have to solve it for ourselves
first so that we can then imagine that
it's possible to have a great
a good conversation and then start to
expect our leaders and elected officials
to actually have the skill too
um and i think that's the only way
forward like i don't think politicians
are gonna solve this regardless of who's
elected
i think they can make it worse in very
different ways um
and uh or do no harm which is also great
don't make it worse um but yeah i
i yeah that said you know i
definitely have a preference for for
politicians and candidates that get
elected
for other reasons
i'll piggyback off that um
i think there's i think there's two kind
there well you know you can you can do
binary models of everybody there's two
kinds of people right you know or
whatever
um but i think that
um some of the frustrations that people
have
now about politics are that
um there's no good leaders and i think
there's
two kinds of people there's some people
who are like you know they make their
own decisions they decide things for
themselves
and then they don't really need a leader
to tell them what to do
but there's some people that do need a
leader to tell them what to do
um and they i think are the ones that
are in the most turmoil
right now um
with the leadership that we have right
and
i think that in order to foster these
productive conversations and whatnot
i think one of the things we have to do
is we have to look to
how do we make it so that people are not
so dependent on leadership to
do their thinking for them and
i don't know the answer to that question
and i wish i did
um because i haven't been thinking about
it long
and maybe that's hopeless and maybe i
need to reframe the question and
come up with a different approach but
that's the thing i've been chewing on
for the last couple of days
and i you know i don't know the answer
my problem is when i get into these
these difficult um i get into difficult
conversations and i start looking at
well
you know how would we solve it and you
know i mean
buster's an optimist and i admire that
and buster and i'm just a pessimist
and maybe we should do a whole letter
thing on optimism and pessimism i don't
know but um
but uh i don't you know i spend a lot of
time looking for hope and i sometimes i
just can't find it because every time
somebody's like oh we can just do this
and i'm like yeah but that's not gonna
work
so um you know but this is positive and
you know if this grows you know maybe we
you need a slogan where if people are
you know pissing on each other on
twitter that it can just be like take it
to me take it the letter
right or some kind of thing like that
where it was like something that's used
to
like i'll meet you on letter it's kind
of like all right
let's go outside you know flagpole yeah
something and um and then maybe you can
get people to start having these
difficult conversations and product more
productive discourses by simply saying
i'm willing to have a productive
discourse or you and then see what they
say
maybe that could work i don't know it's
um and
get with the rathbones and brainstorm up
marketing ideas for a letter or
something i don't know
save us rathbones
on that uh a note uh so this was the
first test of the the postscript series
um i think i might make it 90 minutes
next time
uh it might iterate with some of the
kind of the conversational techniques
and then make it more interactive maybe
going breakout rooms
and also figure out how to kind of
integrate it with the letter platform
um so i'd love to talk to you bj buster
afterwards to figure out maybe how to do
that for part two
i'm trying to get john verveiki and dave
chapman in for the second one because
they had an excellent exchange
um i know john is keen on that so
that being said uh i know clyde
privately messaged me he's putting his
son to bed right now
but dane um do you want to say anything
about letter how people can go on and
check it out if they haven't been there
before
yeah i'll just make a quick quick
comment on the uh take it to letter
because that is
literally the sort of catchphrase that
we've been trying to
promote as a little meme uh when we're
here so
um there's definitely some synergy there
um we haven't quite figured out how to
you know get that to go viral yet but um
there's been some exciting developments
yeah a lot of cat gifts to
um but yeah i mean the competition and
possible competition
uh conversations competitions closed but
you know the battle
of ideas is uh raging on so
if anyone wants to get involved there's
a few ways you can do it you can just go
to letter.wiki it's free to use
anyone can sign up and you can start a
conversation
um you can either write an open letter
encouraging other people
uh to respond but if you have an
interlocutor
in mind it's easiest if you just reach
out to them say hey we'd like to have
this conversation with me
and uh hopefully they agree and then you
both sign up and it's
hopefully the user interface is simple
enough that you can just get the
conversation started
um but you can email me dain karma dot
work if you have any trouble
um and yeah we'd love to have you and
the the more difficult the more
difficult and more important the
conversation the better
so right
great yeah i definitely recommend
checking out it's it's very fun
engaging in the letter exchange as well
i've done multiple myself
um so next week or the week after that's
where the second
edition of the post script is coming on
uh if you have any feedback
message myself you can email me um i'm
thinking about 90 minutes break-up rooms
and stuff like that
uh and uh upcoming events with the stoa
you can check out the website
we have a bunch as always um and if you
like to support the store you can go to
our patreon page
and support us there all right everyone
thank you so much
yeah that's great thank you so much for
putting this together peter
please see you around